this is the story of how the hip thrust
came to be so picture this the year is
2006 the date is October 12th just over
10 years ago as of last week and I'm
sitting in my house in Scottdale at the
time and I'm watching a UFC fight I'm
watching Ken Shamrock fight Tito Ortiz
and I don't care who wins I just want it
to be a good fight but quickly Tito
Ortiz full mounts Ken Shamrock and he's
you know raining down punches and I want
Ken Shamrock to escape I want him to
Buck his hips so he can escape out of
there and the fight lasts longer but
he's not even trying and I'm like he
must not be strong from that position
cuz he's not even trying to escape and I
know from experience because not only
did I fight my twin brother every day of
my life up until we were like 16 I also
did Jiu-Jitsu and while it is a lot
harder to escape full mount with like
really good Fighters if you do have
freakishly powerful hips it helps a lot
so as a certified strength and
conditioning specialist I started
thinking there needs to be an exercise
that that improves a that can help
improve that skill cuz it's not like you
can be like hey bro sit on my hips and
straddle me and I'm going to pump out 30
reps so you need to you need I needed a
way to have resistance and then I
thought you know it's just a little
short range of motion if we could sink
way down you could triple the range of
motion if you had two different you know
surfaces where you could sink your hips
down in the middle and so right then I
thought of an idea and so I go out to my
garage and my girlfriend at the time
Genie's with me I'm like Genie come
outside and help me and so she comes out
in the garage and I'm like we need to
move this glute ham developer next to
this re reverse hyper and so I've had
this this is the exact same piece of
equipment from 10 years ago I've had
these for like 12 or 14 years um but
this is an elite FTS ghd and this is a
west side reverse hyper so she's like
why can't this wait till tomorrow and
I'm like fine you know what just go
inside I'll do it myself and so I moved
this about you know what like 3 4 ft
away from the re reverse hyper and I I
didn't think of using a barbell at that
time I thought of using a dip belt with
weight suspended underneath me and so
here's what it looked like the
picture at that time I used four 45lb
plates not just one so it was way harder
to get into position but just for the
sake of illustrating this to you I will
show you what it looked
like so here's what it look
like and so
So at around the 12th
rep
my left glute felt like it was going to
cramp and I was like oh my God you know
I had been doing squats and deadlifts
and lunges but I never felt that
cramping sensation and so I thought you
know what I need to popularize this
exercise and it sounds kind of lame but
I went outside and I looked up into the
sky and I
my life is going to completely change
from this point forward because I knew I
was going to try and learn as much as
possible about this movement and try to
popularize it as much as
possible and that's been the case over
my past the past 10 years so at that
point I said I got to teach people this
I need to write an article I'll write an
article for testosteron for teenage and
and I'll teach them how to do this and
I'm like oh that's not a good idea
because first of all how many people
have a glute ham developer and a reverse
hyper or something like this and the the
setup is cumbersome people are going to
like to it's really hard when you're
using heavy weight and also it can be
dangerous because let's say you didn't
have rubber surfaces or let's say the
person pushed too hard this way these
can slide apart and you could
theoretically come crashing down and you
know hit your tailbone on on this or
this or something and do some damage so
I I quickly realize this is not a good
idea there needs to be another way there
needs to be a a a prototype I need to
make a prototype I need to make an
apparatus to allow people to perform
this exercise and so I'll show you the
the progression of
of apparatuses that over the years that
allow you to perform the hip
thrust so here is the first prototype
and I call this the scorcher and it's
actually a terrible design but at the
time it's the best I could do and what I
wanted to do was mimic this setup right
here but I got a lot of things wrong so
first of all I realized how hard it is
to get the upholstery right cuz this is
really dense it's not thick enough you
can almost see the ridges in here second
of all at the time I wanted these to
serve as band pegs but also the pegs you
used to adjust the unit and what what I
had to do if you wanted to adjust the
length of the unit I had to go like this
and had to get in here pull both of
these out at the same time and then push
back and do like a kick back to get this
back it was like nearly impossible and
then finally this here had pins that
went through but this doesn't Glide see
how I want it to Glide you have to like
shimmy it into
position but it was a good starting
point and again I had not thought of
using the barbell it was just band
resistance that you could connect to
here and then single leg off of here we
also like to use this guy to do
Bulgarian split squats at the time so um
I quickly realized this was not an ideal
invention so I moved on to the next
version of the
scorcher so here's the next uh scorcher
model and uh this was the next
progression and I really liked it I
still love it to this day but it does
have some issues but this was the model
that I used at my training facility at
the time I had a personal training
studio called lifts it was in a nice
part of Scottdale a guiney ranch and I
had my studio for 2 years and this is
how everybody hip thrusted so every
client I ever had did hip thrust off of
here they started out with body weight
once they could do three sets of 20 we'd
move them to bands and barbell and we
also did single leg off of here and so
here's how it worked uh and and for the
barbell it was kind of if you didn't
have spotters so at at lifts we would
have two of the trainers stand on each
side they would pick the barbell up and
then the person would slide under and
we'd set it in their lap so that worked
great but how many people have two spots
following around throughout life um but
anyway for bands it was easy for barbell
if you didn't have a spotter you had
to the barbell fit in this this design
um I want
you can see how a barbell like with
plates could fit right in here so that
was the idea that plates could fit in
here nice so what you'd have to do is
deadlift the
barbell sit here and then scoot down do
the set and then you'd finish you'd
scoot up and then you'd put the bar back
down now that's great when you're using
135 and 225 but we got up to 405 back
then this is harder than this is harder
than when using uh just a standard bench
so that was all we did back in the day
was 405 for like five reps me and my
trainers could do that it was a pain in
the but you would be exhausted just
doing getting the bar into place and
then putting it back down but here's how
it looks with bands so we would just
pick one of these guys
up and
you slide under like this what was nice
is there's tension on my hips right now
then from here come
up so there's tension throughout the
entire range of
motion tension when you're at the bottom
tension at the top you have this huge
giant foot plate so I can go low I can
go high I can go wide Sumo so this was
great but it did have some issues this
was going to cost a fortune and so at
this point in time
I tried to start thinking of how I could
teach people how to do the hip thrust
without any special
equipment so this might sound silly to
you but even 2 years after I had thought
up the hip thrust I had never thought of
using a standard bench it never even
occurred to me we always used the
scorcher and so at this point in time I
realized I wanted to all my clients at
the time were telling me Brett you need
to popularize your me your the world
needs to be doing this
stuff and I was too tired I was too
drained I'd train people all day long
then I'd work out and then I'd want to
go home and veg out and watch TV because
I was so drained but I decided to close
up my studio and focus
on expanding my reach so I started up a
Blog I started social media and I knew
that I couldn't popularize the hip
thrust if you had to buy an expensive
Giant scorcher in order to perform it so
I started thinking how could I do do
this without any specialized equipment
and then one day I'm like wait I guess
you could use a random bench now it's
nice to have both the hips and the feet
elevated because then you can sink your
hips way down and get even more stretch
on the
hamstrings but it's still a great
exercise just using a standard bench and
so this was the next logical progression
in the well this would probably be the
first logical progression in the hip
thrust Evolution but it took me a couple
years to stumble on this and so one of
the problems with just using a bench
there are a couple of problems number
one if you have giant legs if you're a
big guy you got to roll the barbell over
if you're using padding well one of the
problems is if you're just using the
barbell it hurts your hips you need
padding and so the best thing I've found
so far is the squat sponge I love it so
we use a squat sponge but if you use the
squat sponge and you just use a standard
bar you go to roll it over your legs and
it gets stuck so it's annoying well
right now I'm using the Buffalo Bar so
you see this is curved so it just rolls
right over RS right over the hips so
it's really nice and but one of the
other problems is some of the benches
are really tall if I hip those from
right here this I need my back lower so
what I will need to do as soon as I
start to perform the hip distance I will
need to come up and walk myself up to
about right here come down come up so
that's
currently how I recommend most people
perform the hip thrust from
gyms is get into place come up see how I
elevated myself you don't need to touch
the ground because you might lose that
position so just come about right here
come
up
now I don't like how allow to move stuff
around so we had been performing the hip
thrust off of a standard bench even
though I still have my Scorchers I
wanted to do it Off the Bench just like
everyone else was doing so I could learn
more and teach and better teach people
but eventually I realized I like having
a standalone unit I don't like moving my
benches around this needs to be secured
against something or it can move
backwards I don't want to hip thrust out
of the power rack I want to use my
benches for benching benching so I
wanted to make a unit that people could
buy but I didn't want it to cost you
know $2,000 because most people can't
afford that I wanted to make a unit that
people could use from their homes and so
I came up with the hip
Thruster so this is the hip Thruster and
I have two models this is hip Thruster
1.0 and hip Thruster 2.0 and hip
Thruster 1.0 was nice
um I still have one I still use it but
two M two issues with this one and it's
really not that big of a deal but see
these band pegs they're not optimal and
I'll show you why when I show you uh
this is kind of like how the bands were
with scorcher they bend your they they
ruin your bands over time because of the
way they have to be put in here and uh
and then the second issue is I had this
at about I originally wanted it to be 16
in in height that's about the ideal
height but this padding was so thick
that we ended up um it ended up being
closer to 17 in and so I feel like it's
a little
tall it's okay for me but for a lot of
the women it was too high and so the
next model was the hip Thruster
2.0 and this model is nice because it's
an inch lower and let me tell you a
funny story I got this model right as I
was finished finishing my
PhD and the night that I submitted my
PhD thesis it was like I think it was
the end of July of
2015 uh so it's like July 31st or
whatever let's see J March May June July
yeah 31 days in July so it was July 31st
I submit my thesis at I had to submit it
before midnight and I didn't even care
that it was midnight I just wanted to
celebrate I wanted to work out I go out
into my garage and and I'm feeling on
top of the world and I hip thrusted at
that time my high best hip thrust was
700 well I hit a 725 lb hip thrust which
is that time was my best now I've got
800 lb but I hit a 725 lb hip thrust
which was the most I had ever done
before that was 675 and I was feeling so
good like I got stronger I'm done with
my thesis and then that whole next week
we started using this model and all of
my female clients that week set PRS and
I realized it's not that I got stronger
when you lower the height of the pad
even just an inch it makes a difference
you're stronger with the pad lowered a
little bit and we uh I actually
understand it now from a physics
standpoint after working with these
complicated equations with the
mechanical engineer but yes you're a
little bit stronger with a lowered
height but this works for most people if
we have like 5 foot tall women or um or
you'll probably with 411 to 5'2 or women
that are even taller but have freakishly
long legs and short torsos we use this
guy and you can buy an ER balance pad or
a knockoff yes for all and you sit your
butt there and it effectively it's like
you're lowering the bench height cuz
you're sitting your butt there but
what's really nice about this model is
the band pegs so this is so nice because
if I want to do band hip thrust all I do
is just wrap this
over and then get it right into place
like that so it's just such an ideal
setup now I'm not going to show you
barbell again CU I've showed you that
what I do want to show you is we've also
been using a hip Circle so here's what I
call Double band hip
thrust and I will get this
in I will put this right above my
knees now I'm doubling up the rolls of
the glutes so now I've got to use my my
glutes to keep the knees out to create
hip abduction and external rotation
while I thrust the hips up and down
moving the hips into from flexion into
extension and back down so here's what
this looks like okay get into
place and if you do three sets at 20
with this you will have a glute burn
like you've never felt before
so this is the evolution of the hip
thrust here's where we stand now there's
currently hundreds of variations you can
use all sorts of equipment you can do
feet elevated you can do them off the
ground you can do shoulders elevated you
can Elevate both the shoulders and the
feet you can do them with barbell you
can do with bands you can do them with
combinations of loading you can do
single leg you can do double leg you can
vary your stance with you can vary the
height of ation there's so many
different ways to do it most people can
find several different uh bridging and
thrusting variations that make them feel
their glutes really well but I'm very
proud of this 10-year progression and
I'm committed to Future research and
learning even more as time goes on um
I'm currently involved with a really
cool study that's about to take place
it'll take a couple years but once
that's done we will know so much more
about the hipos and how it compares to
squats and D
for all types of functional
transfer and and also activation and
hypertropic adaptation so I want to
thank everyone for watching this and
thank all the people who have supported
me over the years and who believed in me
and trusted me and didn't say man this
guy who's this crazy guy thrusting all
this weight around you you believed in
me enough to give it a try so thank you
very much